start with a right triangle with sides
of length A and B and a hypotenuse of
length C now draw squares off the side
lengths enclosing an area of a squared
and B squared respectively then draw a
square off the hypotenuse in closing an
area of c squared here's a proof that
the area contained in the C by C square
is equal to the sum of the areas in the
other two squares imagine these two
lines of length C pass through the
center of the B by b square then they
cut the side length of the B by b square
into lengths of B plus a over 2 and B
minus a over 2. we can then take the
four resulting pieces and shift them to
the C by C square like this the leftover
middle piece is also a square and you
can check that the side length is a so
we can shift to a by a square inside
therefore we've seen that c squared
equals B squared plus a squared where A
and B are the leg lengths of a right
triangle with a hypotenuse of length C
this is the Pythagorean theorem As
proved by Henry dudney